Alessandro Simoni

PhD Student @ Department of Engineering "Enzo Ferrari"

Modena, Italy

C +39 334 8040595 | ■ alle.simoni.as@gmail.com | 🛪 alexj94.github.io | 🖬 LinkedIn | 🎓 Google Scholar

Summary _

I am a PhD Student enrolled in the International Doctorate in ICT program at the AlmageLab research group of the University of Modena and Reggio Emilia (Italy), under the supervision of Prof. Roberto Vezzani. My PhD thesis defense is expected to be in March 2024. My research activities are focused on Computer Vision and Deep Learning applied to Collaborative Robotics scenarios, more precisely in topics like 3D Object Reconstruction and 3D Human/Robot Pose Estimation. Moreover, I'm actively involved in two projects in collaboration with two different companies related to 3D Human-Centric Scene Understanding in outdoor video surveillance scenarios and 3D Vehicle Reconstruction in real-world scenarios, respectively.

Knowledge and computer skills _____

Programming languages Python (proficiency), C++, JavaScript **Libraries and Tools** PyTorch, NumPy, OpenCV, PyCharm

Domains Deep Learning, 2D/3D Computer Vision, 3D Human/Robot Pose Estimation, 3D Reconstruction

Spoken languages Italian mothertongue, English C1 (certifed ESOL Cambridge)

Working experiences ____

AlmageLab - University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy July 2023 - (July 2024)

Research grant **Supervisor**: Prof. Roberto Vezzani

Project: "Al platform with digital twins of interacting robots and people"

AlmageLab - University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

Research grant

June 2022 - June 2023

Supervisor: Prof. Roberto Vezzani

Project: "Study of recent combinations of CNN and Vision Transformer architectures"

AlmageLab - University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

May 2020 - May 2022

Research grant

Supervisor: Prof. Roberto Vezzani

Project: "PREVUE - Prediction of Activities and Events by Vision in an Urban Environment"

AlmageLab - University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

Student internship for master's degree thesis

July 2019 - Feb. 2020

Supervisor: Prof. Rita Cucchiara

"Future urban scene generation: a deep learning approach for a 3D temporal vehicle reconstruction starting from monocular images"

Education _____

University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

PhD student - Curriculum "Computer engineering and science"

Nov. 2020 - (Mar. 2024)

Supervisor: Prof. Roberto Vezzani

University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

Master's degree in computer engineering

Sep. 2017 - Feb. 2020

• GPA: 27.806/30. Final grade: 108/110

University of Modena and Reggio Emilia

Modena, Italy

Bachelor's degree in computer engineering

Sep. 2013 - Feb. 2017

• GPA: 23.607/30. Final grade: 91/110

Certifications ____

First Certificate in English (FCE)

Grade A (Score 180, C1), University of Cambridge ESOL Examinations

Dec. 2020

Italian State certification exam for Engineer Profession

Association of Engineers

2021

4^{th} Advanced Course on Data Science and Machine Learning (ACDL 2021)

Participation certificate with final exam

July 2021

16^{th} International Computer Vision Summer School (ICVSS 2022)

Participation certificate with final exam

July 2022

ELLIS Summer School on Large-Scale AI for Research and Industry

Participation certificate with final project (NeRF-based camera optimization)

Sept. 2023

Additional information

Citizenship

Italian, German

Travelling Passport, B license, own car

Speaker at conferences _____

 35^{th} IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems

Kyoto, Japan

 21^{st} International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing

Lecce, Italy

 9^{th} International Conference on 3D Vision

Virtual, Online Virtual, Online

16th VISIGRAPP 25^{th} International Conference on Pattern Recognition

Virtual, Online

Journals and conferences activities _____

 $2^{nd}\,$ T-CAP 2022 Workshop at ICPR2022

Montreal, Canada

Technical Program Committee

21-25 Aug. 2022

 $1^{st}\,$ T-CAP 2021 Workshop at ICIAP2021

Lecce, Italy

Technical Program Committee

23-27 Mag. 2022

16th VISIGRAPP

Virtual, Online

Session chair

8-10 Feb. 2021

Reviewing activities _

IEEE/CVF Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)

IEEE International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR)

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

Towards a Complete Analysis of People: From Face and Body to Clothes (T-CAP)

International Workshop and Challenge on People Analysis (WCPA)

Teaching activities __

School in AI: Deep Learning, Vision and Language for Industry - first edition

Modena, Italy

Laboratory Lecturer - 3D Computer Vision

Feb. 2022

School in AI: Deep Learning, Vision and Language for Industry - second edition Laboratory Lecturer - 3D Computer Vision

Modena, Italy Sept. 2022

Thesis supervision.

MSc Thesis (G. Doganieri)

"3D Multi-Person Pose Estimation and Skeleton tracking by a single RGB camera"

Feb. 2022

Publications _____

More info on Google Scholar.

JOURNALS

Pattern Recognition Letters (PRL)

A.D'Eusanio, A. Simoni, S. Pini, G. Borghi, R. Vezzani, R.Cucchiara "Depth-based 3D human pose refinement: Evaluating the refinet framework"

Mar. 2023

Computers & Graphics

A. Caputo, A. Giacchetti, S. Soso, D. Pintani, A. D'Eusanio, S. Pini, G. Borghi, A. Simoni, R. Vezzani, R. Cucchiara, et al.

Oct. 2021

"SHREC 2021: skeleton-based hand gesture recognition in the wild"

Informatics

A. D'Eusanio, A. Simoni, S. Pini, G. Borghi, R. Vezzani, R. Cucchiara "Multimodal hand gesture classification for the human-car interaction"

Aug. 2020

Udine, Italy

CONFERENCES

16th VISIGRAPP

23^{rd}	International Confe	ence on Image	Analysis and	Processing
-----------	----------------------------	---------------	--------------	------------

D. Di Nucci, A. Simoni, M. Tomei, L. Ciuffreda, R. Vezzani, R. Cucchiara

"CarPatch: A Synthetic Benchmark for Radiance Field Evaluation on Vehicle Components"

11-15 Sept. 2023 Kyoto, Japan

35^{th} International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems + RA-L

A. Simoni, S. Pini, G. Borghi, R. Vezzani

 $\hbox{``Semi-Perspective Decoupled Heatmaps for 3D Robot Pose Estimation from Depth Maps"}$

23-27 Oct. 2022

$21^{st}\,$ International Conference on Image Analysis And Processing

S. Pini, G. Borghi, A. D'Eusanio, A. Simoni, R. Vezzani

"Unsupervised detection of dynamic hand gestures from leap motion data"

Lecce, Italy 23-27 Mag. 2022

$9^{th}\,$ International Conference on 3D Vision

A. Simoni, S. Pini, R. Vezzani, R. Cucchiara

"Multi-category mesh reconstruction from image collections"

Virtual, Online

 16^{th} VISIGRAPP

a. Simoni, a. D'Eusamo, S. Fini, G. Dorgin, R. Vezzani

1-3 Dec. 2021 Virtual, Online

A. Simoni, A. D'Eusanio, S. Pini, G. Borghi, R. Vezzani

"Improving car model classification through vehicle keypoint localization"

8-10 Feb. 2021 Virtual, Online

L. Bergamini, S. Pini, A. Simoni, R. Vezzani, S. Calderara, R. B. D'Eath, R. B. Fisher "Extracting accurate long-term behavior changes from a large pig dataset"

8-10 Feb. 2021

$25^{th}\,$ International Conference on Pattern Recognition

A. Simoni, L. Bergamini, A. Palazzi, S. Calderara, R. Cucchiara "Future urban scene generation through vehicle synthesis"

Virtual, Online 10-15 Jan. 2021

$8^{th}\,$ International Conference on 3D Vision

A. D'Eusanio, A. Simoni, S. Pini, G. Borghi, R. Vezzani, R. Cucchiara "A transformer-based network for dynamic hand gesture recognition"

Virtual, Online 25-28 Nov. 2020

According to law 679/2016 of the Regulation of the European Parliament of 27th April 2016, I hereby express my consent to process and use my data provided in this document and application for recruiting purposes.